Guide to the Paul T. Hanley Papers, 1956-1963
Department of Special Collections
Paul T. Hanley Papers,
1956-1963
Special Collections M0151
Hanley, Paul T.
3 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Dr. P. T. Hanley, 1966.
Scope and Content
Letters, pamphlets and unpublished manuscripts collected by Dr. Hanley to support his doctoral research on the Inter-American Defense Board. Includes letters with former Board chiefs and others connected with the Board.
Biographical Note
Retired military officer.
Container List
- Inter-American Defense College 1963Student Questionnaire (Box 1, Folder 1)
  This notebook contains information and opinions relating to the activities of the Inter-American Defense Board, as well as other organizations important in the Inter-American system. The material was obtained through correspondence, questionnaires, and interviews. Some letters are restricted; see preface to Notebook I.
  The contents are arranged generally by groups of respondents, though adherence to this arrangement is not rigid.
- IADC Faculty Comments and 1964Student Questionnaire
- Army and Air Caribbean Schools
- U.S. Military CINCARIB, etc. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Civic Action, Counterinsurgency
- Professors
- Notebook II (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Contents:
  Former Board Chiefs
  Lt. Gen. Stanley D. Embick
  Lt. Gen. Hugh A. Drum
  Lt. Gen. Matthew B. Ridgway
  Lt. Gen. Willis D. Crittenberger
  Lt. Gen. Charles L. Bolte
  Major Gen. Robert L. Walsh
  Lt. General Howard A. Craig
  Major Gen. Robert W. Douglass, Jr.
  Admiral Edmond T. Wooldridge
  Gen. Lemuel C. Shepherd, Jr.
  Lt. Gen. Lemuel Mathewson
  Lt. Gen. Robert W. Burns
  Lt. Gen. Edward H. Underhill
  Vice Admiral B. L. Austin
- Delegates and Assistants
- IADB Staff, Secretariat, etc. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Ambassadors, Foreign Service, etc.
- OAS AND United Nations
- Historia de la Junta Interamericana de Defensa IADB, Washington, 1961. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Geography of the Organization of American States: A Global View. by Paul Hanley, 1964., Term paper. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Poderio Espacial y Operaciones Aereo-Terrestres. (Spacepower and Air-Ground Operations: U.S.A.F.) by Richard C. Harris, Wilson T. Jones, and Paul T. Hanley. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- The Inter-American Collective Security System, by Paul Hanley, 1956, term paper. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Inter-American Defense College material. Information sheet, program, etc. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Inter-American Defense College, Selected speeches presented to the first class of the IADC. Washington, D.C. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Civic Action. Presentation to Inter-American Defense College, Jan. 29, 1963.Col. Thurlo Ashton, USAF. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Inter-American Defense College, Course Outline, Second Course, June 1963-Nov. 1963. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Bibliographies, Second Class. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Inter-American Defense College, Selected speeches presented to the second class of the IADC, Washington, D.C. (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Guest Speakers, Second Class, June-Nov., 1963. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- News release. Remarks of Paul H. Nitze at the opening ceremony of the IADC, Second Course, 1963. (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Remarks presented at the Graduation Exercises of the Second Course of the IADC, 1963. (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Opening ceremonies, Third Class. IADC, Feb., 1964. (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Inter-American Defense College. Course Outline, Third Course, Feb.-July, 1964. (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Selected Speeches presented to the Third Class of the Inter-American Defense College. Washington, D.C. (Box 2, Folder 20)
- This I Believe, by the Honorable Spark M. Matsunaga, member of Congress. IADC. March, 1964. (Box 2, Folder 21)
- IADC. Course Outline, Fourth Course. Oct-May, 1965. (Box 2, Folder 22)
- IADC. Graduation ceremonies. Fourth Class. May 28, 1965. (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Bibliography for Section II. (Box 2, Folder 24)
- The Inter-American Defense College: A term paper by Doublas W. Davis. (Box 2, Folder 25)
- USAF School for Latin America. 1963prospectus. Caribbean Ari Command, Albrook AFB, Canal Zone. (Box 3, Folder 26)
- USAF School for Latin America. Information Booklet, 1963. (Box 3, Folder 27)
- USAFSLA Questionnaire #1, Sept. 12, 1963. (Box 3, Folder 28)
- USAFSLA Questionnaire #2, Sept. 24, 1963. (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Air Force information policy letter. Supplement for commanders. (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Air Force Civic Action Programs in Latin America. (Box 3, Folder 31)
- The Fifth Annual Inter-American Air Force Chiefs Conference, May, 1965. (Box 3, Folder 32)
- The U.S. Army School of the Americas. Catalog. (Box 3, Folder 33)
- The U.S. Army School of the Americas, History and Current Operations. (Box 3, Folder 34)
- International Police Academy. Class book, general course. May-Aug, 1964. (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Academia Internacional de Policía. Album Academico, curso general, May-Aug., 1964. (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Program Guide to Participant Training in Public Safety. Oct., 1964.Office of Public Safety. (Box 3, Folder 37)
- The West Point Conference on Latin American Problems. April, 1964.U.S. Military Academy. (Box 3, Folder 38)
- The Organization of American States as a Collective Security System, by Robert J. Redington. Industrial College of the Armed Forces, Washington, D.C. 1961-62. (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Boletin de Accion Civica. Fuerzas Armadas de Honduras, Dec., 1962. (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Boletin Informativo. Fuerzas Armadas de Venezuela, no. 23, May, 1962. (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Operacion Fraternidad. Tegucigalpa Honduras. Sept., 1962.Directiva del Ejercicio, no. 1. (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Informacion General Sobre La Operacion America (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Conferencia Inter-Americana Do Exercito. Relatorio Final. Forte Amador, Zona Do Canal, July, 1961. (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Third Conference of The American Armies. Final Report. Fort Amador, Canal Zone, July, 1962. (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Conference of the American Armies. Final Report. Fort Amador, Canal Zone, July, 1963. (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Conference of the American Armies. Report of the Proceedings, U.S. Military Academy, Aug., 1964. (Box 4, Folder 47)
- Third Annual Inter-American Air Force Chiefs Conference, May 1963. (Box 4, Folder 48)
- IV Annual Inter-American Conference of Air Force Chief and Chiefs of State. Final Report on Work Done, May, 1964. (Box 4, Folder 49)
- Civic Action in Latin America, by David Thompson. Term paper. (Box 4, Folder 50)
- The Caribbean Commission and Western Security, by Norman Pianalto. Term paper. (Box 4, Folder 51)
- Senator Smathers' Proposal for an Inter-American Military Peace-Keeping Force, by Linda Lee Eckberg. Term Paper. (Box 4, Folder 52)
- Remarks on the attitudes of Canadians towards the Organization of American States and a discussion of the arguments for and against Canada's becoming a Member, by H. E. Sadler, term paper. (Box 4, Folder 53)
- Inter-American Treaty of Reciprocal Assistance (Rio Treaty) and The Charter of the Organization of American States, by Thornton Robison. Term paper. (Box 4, Folder 54)
- The National War College. Memorandum for members of the faculty and class. (Box 4, Folder 55)
- Collective Security Through the Organization of American States, by Arthur Hurow. Army War College Student Thesis. (Box 4, Folder 56)
- Regional Collective Security and the Organization of American States, by Lt. Col. Max R. McCarthy. Army War College Thesis. (Box 4, Folder 57)
- Role of the Military in the Organization of American States, by Lt. Col. Francis S. Bodine. Air War College Thesis. (Box 4, Folder 58)
- Is a Military Force for the Organization of American States Feasible?, by Kenneth P. Burns. Army War College Student Thesis. (Box 4, Folder 59)
- United Nations. Towards a dynamic development policy for Latin America. New York, 1963. (Box 5, Folder 60)
- Foro Internacional. Revista Trimestral publicada por el Colegio de México. V. 4, no. 1, Julio-Sept., 1963. (Box 5, Folder 61)
- Social Progress Trust Fund. Inter-American Development Bank. Third Annual Report, 1963. (Box 5, Folder 62)
- Latin America. Trends in Production and Trade. Statistics and Reports Division. Agency for International Development. Oct., 1963. (Box 5, Folder 63)
- Applications of the Inter-American Treaty of Reciprocal Assistance, 1948-1956.Pan American Union. Washington, D. C., 1957. (Box 5, Folder 64)
- The Alliance for Progress: A hemispheric response to a global threat. Chamber of Commerce of the United States, Washington, D. C., 1963. (Box 5, Folder 65)
- Kemnitzer, William J. The Alliance For Progress. Lecture given at The American Institute for Foreign Trade. April 8-May 28, 1963. (Box 5, Folder 66)
- How Much Progress? Alliance for Progress. A report to the publisher of Time, by John Scott. (Box 5, Folder 67)
- The Alliance for Progress: its second year. 1962-1964.Pan American Union, Washington, D. C., 1964. (Box 5, Folder 68)
- Report to the Inter-American Economic and Social Council presented by the government of the U.S.A. Washington, D.C., Sept., 1963. (Box 5, Folder 69)
- U.S. Assistance to Latin America. Obligations and Loan Authorizations, Fy 1953 - Fy 1964.Agency for International Development. Washington, D.C. (Box 5, Folder 70)
- Organization of American States. Annual Report of the Secretary General, 1961. (Box 5, Folder 71)
- The Organization of American States. Report submitted by the Pan American Union to the 11th Inter-American Conference. 1954-59. 1959. (Box 5, Folder 72)
- OAS 10th Inter-American Conference, Caracas, Venezuela, 1954.Report of the Activities of the Organization of American States, 1948-1953.Submitted by the Pan American Union to the 10th Inter-American Conference. 1953. (Box 5, Folder 73)
- Lyndon B. Johnson, Freedom, Peace and Progress for the Americas. OAS- Pan American Union. Information Series, no. 3, 1963. (Box 5, Folder 74)
- Translations on Cuba, no. 57. U.S. Dept. of Commerce, Joint Publications Research Service. June, 1963. (Box 5, Folder 75)
- 76 American Republics. External Research completed studies. Bureau of Intelligence and Research. Fall 1963-Winter 1964.
- Educational Data: Cuba. U.S. Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare. Nov., 1962. (Box 5, Folder 77)
- Dean Rusk. Report to the Nation: The Punta del Este Conference. The Dept. of State, 1962. (Box 5, Folder 78)
- American Republics establish an Alliance for Progress. The Dept. of State. Inter-American Series 73. October, 1961. (Box 5, Folder 79)
- Inter-American Defense Board, Year Book, 1950 and 1952 (Box 6, Folder 80a)
- Junta Interamericana de defensa-1273. Consejo de Delegados, Apendice 2, acta, Sesion 102, 22 de Abril de 1954,Yearbook for 1953 (Box 6, Folder 80b)
- Inter-American Defense Board, Council of Delegates, Appendix 1, minutes, session 129, 23 June 1955.Yearbook for 1954 (Box 6, Folder 80c)
- Inter-American Defense Board, session 168, Appendix 3, 26 Apr. 1956.Yearbook for 1955 (Box 6, Folder 80d)
- Inter-American Defense Board, Yearbook 1956,Appendix 2, minutes, session 191, 21 Mar. 1957 (Box 6, Folder 80e)
- Inter-American Defense Board, Yearbook 1956, 1 July 1956-30 June 1957,appendix 7, minutes, session 215 (Box 6, Folder 80f)
- Inter-American Defense Board, Yearbook 1957, 1 July 1957-30 June 1958,appendix 2, minutes, session 260, 31 July 1958 (Box 6, Folder 80g)
- Inter-American Defense Board, Yearbook 1958, 1 July 1958-30 June 1959,appendix 2, minutes, session 302, 10 Sept. 1959 (Box 6, Folder 80h)
- Inter-American Defense Board, Yearbook 1959, 1 de Julio-30 de Junio 1960,Secretaria, 25 de Julio de 1960 (Box 6, Folder 80i)
- Inter-American Defense Board, Yearbook 1960, 1 July 1960-30 June 1961,Secretariat, 20 July 1961 (Box 6, Folder 80j)
- Inter-American Defense Board, Yearbook 1961, 1 July 1961-30 June 1962,Secretariat, 18 Dec. 1962 (Box 6, Folder 80k)
- Inter-American Defense Board, Yearbook 1962, 1 July 1962-30 June 1963,Secretariate, 15 July 1963,(with memorandum) (Box 6, Folder 80l)
- Inter-American Defense Board, Yearbook 1963, 1 July 1963-30 June 1964,Secretariat, 22 June 1964,with memorandum (Box 6, Folder 80m)
- Inter-American Defense Board, Yearbook 1964, 1 July 1964-30 June 1965,Secretariat, 20 July 1965 (Box 6, Folder 80n)
- It Is Not Too Late in Latin America. Proposals for Action Now by J. Peter Grace. n.d. (Box 6, Folder 81)
- Organization of American States. Pan American Union, General Secretariat, Organization of American States. Suggestions for the Study of Latin America. n.d. (Box 6, Folder 82)
- Special Consultative Committee on Security. Pan American Union. Report of the Special Consultative Committee on Security on the Work Done During its Fifth Regular Meeting, October 18 to November 10, 1965. (Box 6, Folder 83)
- Special Consultative Committee of Security Against the Subversive Action of International Communism. Initial General Report. 1962 (Box 6, Folder 84)
- Toward a Free World... [Air University, Maxwell Air Force Base, Alabama] (Box 6, Folder 85)
- The Inter-American System: Its Evolution and Role Today. Pan American Union, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 86)
- Alliance for Progress. Official Documents Emanating from the Special Meeting of the Inter-American Economic and Social Council at the Ministerial Level. Held in Punta del Este, Uruguay from August 5 to 17, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 87)
- Special Study Mission to Latin America: Peru, Ecuador, Colombia, Panama, Costa Rica. Committee on Foreign Affairs, House of Representatives, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 88)
- President Kennedy speaks on The Alliance for Progress (Box 6, Folder 89)
- The Alliance for Progress: Its Program and Goals by Teodoro Moscoso (Box 6, Folder 90)
- The Inter-American Defense Board: An Introduction to Mutual Security Planning by the American Republics. Inter-American Defense Board (Box 6, Folder 91)
- The Department of State. American Republics Establish an Alliance for Progress. Reprint from the Department of State Bulletin (Box 6, Folder 92)
- Introduction to the Latin American Republics. Pan American Union (Box 6, Folder 93)
- Council of the Oganization of American States, 15 June 1963.Report of the Alliance for Progress Presented by Senator Juscelino Kubitochek, former President of Brazil (Box 6, Folder 94)
- Council of the Organization of American States, 15 June 1963.Report on the Alliance for progress Presented by Dr. Alberto Lleras, former President of Colombia (Box 6, Folder 95)
- Alianza para Progreso, folder, press releases, brochures (Box 6, Folder 96)